hello welcome everyone it is October
25th 2023 we're in active inference for
the social
sciences and today we're in a discussion
section it is AAL and I and we'll start
off by just saying hello and kind of
reflecting on where we're at with the
course
then we have the questions form that is
on the course website it's in the video
description feel free to submit
questions via this form and then today
we're going to look at the questions
that have been submitted and not
answered yet and we'll just give some
thoughts on them also look for more
questions to arise in the live chat so
with
that what do you want to begin with AVL
feel free to give any kind of overview
or statement and then we'll jump to the
specific questions that have been
submitted before today and during
today the only statement that I want to
make is the last presentation I did
so prediction cause constraints to exist
would be our
wealth uh sorry of that but I really I
don't have anything
to to say that he's more
specific right now all right well this
should be pretty fun let's jump into
some
questions
okay what are the challenges and
potential Solutions in using active
inference to model Collective behaviors
with various environmental
constraints
[Music]
um uh so the uh challenges first is that
in any model you have to pick what you
include and what you did not include so
when you talk about boundary conditions
when you talk about what's including the
model you have to make hypothesis like
if I tell you model I don't know country
that is under sanctions like North Korea
Russia okay how do you model that do you
make a state Bas for every possible
product like every Dimension accounts
for a specific product or type of
product and you have zero if you have
access to sorry a zero if you don't have
access to it and one is you access to it
okay but what if we have new things that
happen that that that is not very useful
if you're interested is an innovation or
something so we will have to make
specific par that uh will traduce
specific questions that you want to ask
the model and using active INF front
has no like does not change anything to
that
and where it is relevant is that um you
can have uh endogenous evolution of
constraints using Acer
I think in a more meaningful sense than
you have with a pure let us say hean or
like non
representational uh framework or
framework that is presentational but
where the space representation is like
hardcoded so you there is a space of
models let us say of evolution of social
norms where I think active inference
would have
a a nedge because active inference is
built to represent normativity and
intentionality and it is not the case to
my knowledge of other like either
dynamicist or cognitivist um Frameworks
for
modeling
could you maybe restate and go into a
little more detail was it
non-representational or indirect
specification of
what of the um beliefs of the system so
what's being directly specified what's
directly specified and then what is
being indirectly
specified inactive inference yeah
inactive inference you have at least in
a sense uh correspondence between
dynamical constraints like information
over where system is and belief that the
system holds that are akin to Norms or
like inal States so beliefs or
intentions
are things that are going on inside and
to my knowledge there is no framework
that makes an explicit foral connection
between the two You' have damis
framework uh where you have stuff that
happens and there is no presentation or
intentional States and you have things
like utility Theory where you have to
specify uh preemptively what are the
interntional states of the
agents which
are um not very relevant toes um like
the enous evolution of social
constraints within a collective
system uh so um
situation where active inference would
be useful is to
model I uh I will try to remember the
term that kofman used kofman
Fillin and
Fillin in
um so I will share the can can we both
share the screen no we can't you can add
it directly
in in this um Coda
page probably a little easier than
all just go to the backend course Coda
page and then follow the token yep and
then go to the questions table and pop
it out you don't have the questions that
is on your
screen just click on
little
um uh challenges and potential Solutions
and then pop it
out pop out
what um just like next to the row see
this expand row and then you'll be in
the same
place what is the row C there is no
letter no no no no just look visually at
the expand
row look visually at the expand row just
click the expand
row on the question that we're
addressing and you'll pop into this
campus the question that we are
addressing is not on the page at least
on my terminal so are you looking at the
public front end or at the course back
end I'm looking at the back end okay and
I do not have the question what are blah
blah
blah oh it is a sub
question what other CH she is okay okay
cool all
right
fun you were talking about Kaufman
though what was
it yes it's a paper that the cosigned
was manator
isin critic of economic uh like I say
rationality but now they say it's Bing
rationality so the um dictionary of
cognitive biases approach to modeling
human
behavior and uh basically the point of
the paper as I understand it is that you
have an evolution of the goals and Norms
uh that shape a social
ecology and this kind of open-ended uh
evolution of the intentional state of
the agent I think is can be addressed in
a more meaningful way with
Acer than with any other formal
framework I
of there are several other aspects I
think so first to kind of restate the
the challenges at then go to the
potential Solutions and the
advantages um like the advantages in
principle and in
practice you started with identifying
like the
major any kind of
modeling challenges so ACM inherits from
all of these modeling challenges or
areas that that are difficult to step
aside from and then yes depending on the
resources of the group and whether it's
2023 or 2 you know future time when
there's different tooling so that is
just about the the challenge of active
inference sometimes compared today with
more off-the-shelf approaches which also
may or may not work but in an acadm
you'll be spending your time making
something that may or may not work may
or may not be orders of magnitude more
just sophistication of a modeling
setting than the team is ready to again
that's a General modeling point but it's
also very easy to get into with ACM and
to jump the gap between something that
is pedagogical and helps show something
like intuitive or
cool and making something for example
that can be used in high reliability
settings and that's a jump that hasn't
been necessarily conveyed in the open
source setting so it's difficult to see
examples of whereas there's kind of like
production type machine learning
algorithms that can at least be no
that's just a little general point so
what are some
advantages there's some really
interesting concepts related to this
like indirect specification so like
let's just say that we were talking
about the mountain car example or a
social variable that seemed to be moving
within a certain
range then the direct encoding of that
can
straint would um be basically made
outdated okay now the landscape changes
and then all of a sudden the mountain
car can go twice as far to a different
direction so if that constraint had been
explicitly
encoded about cognitive um variables or
about the exposition of the mountain car
then the model goes stale but if what's
encoded is somehow a relation with the
agent in the environment so the Mountain
car has 10 horsepower and it can go left
or right as its affordances and
everything that builds from there and
then here's the laws of physics or
mechanics such that here's the weight of
the car and and
then if the landscape changes or his
model is
changing then you get oh yeah now it can
go further or shorter in this
direction but that's like an outcome of
the relationship between the agent in
the
environment explicitly represented as
such versus just looking at the outcome
and then putting constraints on the
outcome yes uh to say we have uh
historically the concept of explanation
that we have inherited from the uh 19th
20th century is uh that we explain by
having a Love full relationship between
variables and to do that we have to
press specify what are the relevant
variables and this is not the thing that
exist with open-ended evolutionary
Dynamics this is all in the um Galu
ctive agency something something
paper so
um and so uh when we ask questions to a
model we don't want to have the answer
yeah it will evolve ously we don't
really know this is not what is expected
basically so we tend not to look at toer
ended Evolution
Dynamics I would say that active
inference has uh some leverage to
represent that that other the framework
would not have because of the
relationship between uh like constraints
as a remal thing and beliefs as an
intentional
state
yeah one thing that makes me think of so
when we're when we're doing modeling
based uh uh outcome based
modeling whether for hobby or for grad
school for a job like we're
often in a setting that either expects
or Rewards or accepts only a
converging
answer because uh because it's being you
know does insulin in dropa change their
circadian this or that it's like that's
it's very it's very converged of a
question already and it's something
where we're looking to reduce our
uncertainty about um so then
that um closes off I mean to the extent
that it converges it closes off
Divergent routes not just of like doing
and addressing that question that's more
of a methodological point but it then we
we don't um make models that
[Music]
can see a more
open-ended Horizon of what could
actually happen in the
system because that always adds
more State spaces that can be broken and
unfolded so I guess again to the kind of
Kernel of the question you've written
these
very interesting sequence of papers
about symmetry breaking and
and all of this so how do you use that
in a way that goes beyond just stating
larger and larger State
spaces or feeling less and less
confident when it seems like a large
piece of this is that certain aspects of
systems are unpre
statable sorry confident about what
precisely
unpre
statable
unpressable yes I'm confident that
uh you cannot preate the space of
possibilities of space of belief that an
agent can have and not devop any
Evolution something that could like that
is by definition of the terms something
that could be argued is that there is no
such thing as a plan Evolution but that
would be
a that would be a a very uh bold thing
to claim and most people would not say
that explicitly ever because
it's kind of obviously not the case if
there is an arent for it I'd like to
hear
it but the argument that
um are uh stated against the upper andd
Devolution thing are um
um basically you have um I would say all
rely on a confusion between the fact
that the law of physics work which they
do and the idea that the specific
language that physics talks is a full
and objective representation of
everything there is or could be which is
like it's a possibility we can discuss
about it but this is a distinct
possibility that the statement that the
law of physics work which again they
do okay cool well then just to sort of
close on this active advantages many
interesting conceptual advantages we
hope analytical and
more uh transdisciplinary or more
holistically and also another
huge piece is it's connected to an
always improving open-source
computational
environment we expect and prefer but in
that case linking a system in year X
social system or model it's kind of like
using a Linux system that there could be
some developments like in message
passing algorithms or
interoperability of different generative
models or category theoretic
augmentation of models that are
connected to the active inference
ontology all these different kinds of
synthetic Technologies which we can
basically already imagine and to some
extent already
have it
becomes uh a way to map systems
to um a lot and that that is not as far
as I understand um plausible without
kind of a first principles and the
ecosystems of share intelligence and all
these other kind of memes and themes
that we talk about all the
time surprise minimization things doing
as most likely for them to do Paths of
least action basium
mechanics then there's a continuity of
explanation with the rock just being
there and the investor trading with this
strategy an
instrumental unifying account
that makes relatively
minimal claims about the territory that
includes the Rock and the investing
activity what' you add
in uh but um like what you said message
passing is uh interesting to me because
you have a broad Coalition of physicist
mathematicians or scientist people in
Academia who basically think there is
one language to Nature and what we do as
scientist is to discover it and I I do
not think that holds water not only
because of an evolution is a thing uh
which is a sufficient actually but if
you look at Mage passing if you look at
Quantum bism if you look at category
Theory you open formally and
conceptually the possibilities that
there are different languages in the
world and they may be more or less in
their operation
and they may be non-reducible to each
other and then you start to ask Liv
questions I'd
say especially when uh implicitly or
explicitly you are interested in what
determines the fact that a specific
language Works in a specific context why
is
um yeah I'm not not going to go further
down the math road
but
you have important uh compatibility SL
inter operability result between major
fields of uh
physics
um I will give a reference by John B B I
don't know you pronounce it I never
this
base
so we have important interoperability
results in uh fields of physics and
formal
science
and yeah we don't have a proof however
that um you
know all possible presentation of
physics are
interoperative operable
op how do you say that interoperable
interoperable interoperable okay so
from No it's it's it's a great point and
what's really interesting is like the
relationship
between base graphs first off base
graphs being
analytically described and then
computationally implementable is on the
order of decades old and then as we kind
of explored just yesterday in Liv stream
55.0 the relationship between the Bas
graph
and forny graphs which enabled message
passing to be done procedurally to
optimize a base graph which just brings
all of these computational all these
analytical connections but that wasn't
understood until it was and that was
only slightly over two decades
ago so
then in fact those kinds of results and
developments
reflect
the the changing social and scientific
Niche so I don't know maybe this is a
different question but
science as a social
activity and then I don't know does that
how does that ground our work or give us
more
what so
um about um the whole language thing uh
I don't don't know where it's at now but
at least 10 years ago it um seemed that
you can have a message passing you can
have well you can have Bas and
coherence of state of observable that
does not reely explicitly on the
probabilities uh as in a disposition
that is embedded in a specific set space
you can have Bas in coherence that
pre-exist to the representation in which
probity is
embedded and if there was a way to cross
this and message passing You' have
pretty straightforward
straightforward um road to
uh a straight account of contextuality
and social construction I say this with
SC quotes oh great great note exciting
for um Quantum context and Quantum
social and scripts and constraints and
Norms let's close that question for now
though nice
okay
um how can yeah great question thank you
to whoever asked and again video
description you can ask it'll appear and
we we'll see if anyone writes more
questions during the
stream how can or does a framework
Theory principle of everything
articulate with moral normative ethical
deontic
considerations so I I think it is uh
addressed in
uh a good on of detail by an activists
how you relate a theory of biological
individuation to a theory of
Ethics uh I do not have a good grip on
this literature so you have um like how
to say
high level intuitive uh opinion on that
but this is not like state-ofthe-art
and
um okay basically I I uh I'd say this
flows well with stoic virtue
etics things act according to the nature
so you may as well work so that your
nature is good and then you have a
record I ity in counting what is good
and what is not and I do not see um
straightforward analytical way to
resolve this
ambiguity I said circularity or vity
both
apply yeah so I think Evan Thompson has
worked
n and may have a much
better answer to how we relate theories
of being and theories of physics oh
verilla did
actually
yeah I guess my sort of short answer
would there there would be F
first
just we would have to hear a lot more
even possible perspectives but without
even hearing them can at least maybe say
that there is an articul
and a meter stick as an
instrument and this kind of goes
actually to that question about the B
spaces and uh what is preconditioned so
in what ways is the meter
stick
[Music]
um articulate with
Downstream ethical
Frameworks what ought to be done or just
normative more broadly um
there's Downstream decisions that the
meter stick is agnostic to and then the
meter stick is also a
social result that is itself Downstream
of other norms and
constraints biotic abiotic
constraints regularities
of
space
time I would say there is a
um what we can do with a theory of sense
making with active influence or in
activism is to um like
just describe what we mean by
normativity Antics what are the
underlying natural processes when I say
natural what mean by opposition to
social those processes are biological
and social at the same
time
and that that may bring refle ctivity or
distance uh to account of normativity
that may Pro prove some of them
incoherent or uh ill advised that will
not give you a solution to what is
ethical and what is
not notably because um like the most
natural way to
um derive ethics from something like an
activism or something like inference is
that you both those framework are
centered around biological
individuation so we may say that
biological individuation is good
actually that sound sensible but then
the question is biological ination for
whom because you have a right I guess or
desire will at least to exist but SOS
cancer cells within your body who trumps
who I don't know not from a Pur account
there is
no like there is no way you can
straightforwardly anly derive a
prescriptive notion of good from any
physics any descriptive account of the
world you will have when you do when you
make normative claims you have goals
because you are living thing and because
of active inference SL activism we know
that cognition is embedded intivity in
the uh autonomy in the biological
activity of the agent so the theory that
you're framing is in some way motivated
even if you don't know how or at need
that it is and then I'd say from there
it
doesn't quite destroy the project of an
objective systemics but it makes it much
harder to
defend so yeah I'd say you can derive a
lot of negative results from descriptive
theory of um like I wouldn't say ethics
because ethics are non descriptive but
descriptive theory of how ethics to be I
would say that it is uh hard if not
impossible to derive um like positive
results if someone tried to do it I I'd
like to see what this
is wow thank you AO that last piece was
very interesting many results
many many ant colonies with their
behavior to model many real situations
to understand social constraints and
Norms
in
instrumentally with descriptions that
are then in the discussion section of
the
paper and the data are the data and
those are the descriptive aspects it's
it's a different kind of data in a
slight way but there's already enough to
describe and interpret from what would
be merely described and it is very hard
to D derive
positive results first it's a hard
domain to make positive results in not
not just ones that make people feel good
but by positive like positivism like um
Justified true assertions about a
metaphysical space so it's hard to
derive positive results about
normativity and the kind of areas that
this person asked these are all areas
that are are
um
and it's hard to use a quantitative
Theory which is almost it's an
abstraction or it's just one language
it's hard to use
that to make positive
results external to the system harder to
make external to the system positive
results internal to the system are dime
a dozen but then to really make that
reflexive Loop that you
described between the um the what is and
what what we expect and
prefer which is actually woven up in an
interesting way in
actm rather than two kind of diverge
timelines like what we quote expect to
happen like a prediction of the
likeliest future and then a second
timeline that's like well what what what
I would really prefer to be
doing in di the agent just has one
expectation SL
preference which loads up on the
pragmatic
value but that gives a
unified approach towards one's
expectations of how things will be and
what they expect SL prefer them to
be
I would say that at the vibe check level
active inference flows well with the
idea that empowerment is good
actually
but make it a formation would be uh
quite
hard you could say that France Vibes
well with the notion that everyone
knowing their place is good which is
quite the
Opposites so I don't see an ambigous
relation between active inference and
any
um ethical framework I can think
of I would say again that it uh like
flows well with a virtue ethics
framework because of the relation
between uh one's action and one's nature
according to AC inference nature being
here a term that is like maybe not not
the best term but like I'm I'm literally
using a traduction of uh uh before
Christ text so yeah nature is not that
bad just not what we mean uh in the
context of 19s 20s
discussions yeah that's a very complex
topic with with definitely a lot of Rich
work on
like our cities and people nature are
humans
animals and uh that sort
of homo sapiens type
discourse and then how does active
inference frame the relationship with
the niche in terms of entanglement or
communication or co-action
intraaction communication and in
influence
through blanket what
where does that go beyond just
describing it doesn't have to I think a
sort of base level and what you referred
to here is
like that artifact the product of the
work which is what the work is about can
be a jumping off point for other
directions and so the work of active
inference modeling can be in what it
leads
to
it's not
always internal to the model that
the improved awareness or better
decision is
realized uh I can see one quite
straightforward and
I don't think it is entirely broken way
to relate ethics to active infen is
uh
A6 like not not A6 normativity as a
social f it is a collective fomen it's
about social
relationships and you could apply uh
descriptive theory of human
behavior and like human social
aggregated Collective
Behavior Uh
to find out what traits in US
organization are prone to survival or
adaptivity and you could say that those
traits are uh good
actually by construction of what we mean
by ethics that could be a coherent claim
and then you could be interested in what
trades make a
organization
durable but I see this is the only
logically right for why I see but that
would like tend to
um identify as good things that uh I
would not say as good like theodism it
lived quite a long
time well theodism let us say
um old school Empires with no claim to
representations or uh Power by the uh
how do you say
populace and you could uh integrate uh
you could basically um renormalize this
Theory not around uh clock time but
around I don't know metric of Lifetime
how much things happen within the
organization and then you'd start having
something that is less obviously
wrong and you could have a basically
eics
be about optim iation of specific
parameters that can be addressed by
descriptive framework but you'd have to
make a lot of jumps to get
there and while I do not see an obvious
problem to that it is very possible
that we would not like the conclusion of
such optimization thing and again if you
want to model something you have to
decide what are the parameters of
interest and and you can be wrong about
that so here again you do not have an
ambigous even at a purely descriptive
level you do not have an ambigous
application of anything to
anything would say that more empowerment
is good
actually and I would say this goes that
many nested scales of
organization and I would say it as
somehow something to do to the physics
of biological individuation
but only in a Vibe check
way nothing wrong with that
um yeah especially with some of the
recent work like the variational
synthesis with E
evoo and the connections between the
statistical concepts of persistence or
thinkness
from free energy principle related to to
remeasurement of the Observer or the
organism of thems that concept of
repeated measurement being compatible in
our work and and in other related Works
basically with
Fitness if there's a height distribution
of trees in the forest and then a
certain time Point later the height
distribution is the
same that was
stabilizing
Dynamics we could say stabilizing
Evolution or stabilizing
selection if it moved it
moved and so how do since there is such
a coupling between things being as they
are and
basically what the distribution of what
is there is described both this stoic
way but also this kind of evolutionary
biology
way so does of inference offer
any other or complimentary perspective
other than
just the kind of strengths and
weaknesses of
the of using
Fitness phenotypic Fitness or mtic
Fitness as its own
justification to say that is to say that
something is good because it exists this
is not a strong position to
take so this is why you'd have
um
quite high level of difficulty to
um uh derive anything prescriptive from
anything
descriptive the function is not the same
you can make relation between the two no
eics is purely um blind about nature no
um the of nature is purely ethically
um
unmotivated but to have formation
between the two is probably not possible
at least highly
non-trivial okay so to kind of close on
this
question how does a free energy
Principle as a principle for every and
active inference as an implementable
framework for applying free energy
principle systems how does that
articulate with these
broader
very um deep and
fundamental Human Social context short
answer seems to
be it's a lot like other scientific
ideas inherits a lot of
their challenges and frictions and and
situations also there appeared to be
some interesting promising routes or
themes to weave
in however even with a very charitable
or optimistic
interpretation there seems some in
principle challenges with these
areas that make certain kinds of claims
perhaps not even within the
proximate understanding we have of
active inference
but people should totally write in the
live chat or add comments and stuff I
mean it's just interesting
question
okay how are higher order beliefs about
doing better than expected at PM
probably prediction error minimization
integrated into the architecture of the
agent's internal model of external
Dynamics and itself in those Dynamics my
thought here is that we have prior
beliefs to fulfill certain self-
evidencing expectations EG homeostatic
predictions but how do those interact
with these higher order predictions
which appear to my mind to deny or
negate the fundamental priors in so far
as they predict the agent to go over and
above the levels of prediction error
minimization which otherwise might be
achieved by fulfilling those fundamental
priors they gave their thought let's
return to the original
question I do not know like I know that
um a comparison to a basine homeostatic
level of
tionation is a quite important thing in
a
patry notably in the work of
bars I do not know how that's
implemented actually in computational
models so I'd rather not answer
approximatively
uh Ben White should be more informed
about these
things yeah or maybe
you
well I mean the word that seems to be
doing the work is integrated
so higher beliefs about doing better
than expected at prediction error
minimization or we can just say free
energy minimization so this was explored
in the affective
inference
work so if
the um free
energy
was um decreasing as expected it was
associated with neutral veilance if
things were improve proving better than
expected it was associated with positive
veilance and if things
were doing worse than
expected it was negative
veilance so because of the ability to
make hierarchical otim
models and just hierarchical basian
models in general it is possible to talk
about these beliefs about beliefs
metacognitive beliefs so it is possible
to make
models that
have expectations about how well even an
optimization process is going to go and
then a computational psychiatrist or
whatever May associate that with the
affect how is that integrated
into the agent's internal model of
external Dynamics well shortest answer
is to sketch it out how one sees it and
then it becomes either there or not but
just in general if the internal
Model includes these higher order
beliefs about doing better than
expected then that's the agents
generative model that then interfaces or
articulates with external
Dynamics so you could have some
environment that has a environmental
regularity or Dynamics or that are
influenceable or or not and then you
could deploy two agents one of them that
has the Baseline generative model and
the other one has this doing better than
expected layer that the questioner is
asking about and then they can do
parameter sweeps and maybe adding this
higher order belief increases the state
space a lot and so it increases the
computational cost a lot but some
interesting pockets of behavior are
found or the behavior in that setting
ends up looking the exact same but in
another setting it would have been
different a lot of these questions Point
towards very
important
modeling
questions which can basically only be
pointed at because so much is going to
depend on what the actual model
is okay
um where can I find the recommended
reading list mentioned in the
[Music]
lectures
so where we have the um slides from the
lecture they're in live streams just go
to the big table and find the slides if
you find a lecture that doesn't have
slides just let us know and we'll we'll
add it
um where things were just mentioned in
the lectures that's a great question and
our goal at the Active inference Journal
Beyond just transcribing and Publishing
and adding captions and translating and
everything of these live streams
we would like to also do more
bibliographic work so that the books
that people mention we can also have in
that open-source versioned
Journal so we generate the first version
of transcript people update it improve
it oh what was the name of that author
what book are they talking about here
and then we can actually have a unified
bibliography section for the Stream So
if that sounds interesting to you
and you'd benefit from it then surely
many many others will too so if you're
excited to do that kind of active
inference Journal work I highly
encourage SL recommend
it I what else will you
at
same I kind have nothing to
yeah
okay
well we can look at some of the other
questions that were added that others uh
wrote people in live chat can add
question or they can go to the um course
website
and ask a new
question do you want
to look at one of the previous ones
or do you have any other Just Thoughts
you want to bring up
not really the first ones were on sword
so I don't not like and they are
they they were asked weeks ago so there
is a relatively low likelihood that
going over them again would be very
helpful I think we can cut the
discussion cool but the important things
that are not treated now can be Tre in
conclusion
anyway um okay so what are the next
steps then for the
course next step is did a lot of people
register for the uh presenting in the
conclusion
session I haven't gotten any specific
responses or like titles
yet okay so we see if people uh do that
and yeah we can write write another
message um including even a short video
message or just a written one and then
also ask specific
people also if anyone is like interested
to present something but they're not
really sure the format or they want to
pre-recorded we're just kind of
exploring and seeing what the people who
are following along
live want to do and also trying out
things that we think Futures will want
to do
too so if someone has an idea on that
we're definitely open to
it
any last
thoughts nope I'm good cool all right
thank you
then see you
all
bye
that